A Guide to the Nathaniel Parker Willis Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6991-f
Nathaniel Parker Willis Collection 1835-1863
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6991-f
71 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 1963 Dec 17 ] 1966 Sep 12
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "Yours very truly, N. P. Willis", n. d.; Autograph
  - Quotation beginning, "If there is a feature of the human soul.. .", 1849; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " Impromptu ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Tipped to paper with engraving of Ashland; marked Page 5.]
  - Essay, "Jottings-down about the time of the Queen's Marriage", n. d.; AMs, 10 p.
  - Poem beginning, "My Mother! in thy prayer tonight.. .", n. d.; AMs, 2 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Now I have seen a kadji.. .", n. d.; AMs, 2 p.
    [Includes ANS on verso to "Dear Sir" stating that the three verses he sent him are from his poem "
    The Lady Jane
    . "]
  - Poem, " Thou Hereafter ", n. d.; AMs, 1 p.
    [Includes attached autograph; page is marked 3.]
  - Poem, " Toujours Perdrix ", 1864 Mar 21; AMsS, 1 p.
    [From "
    Lady Jane
  - Poem beginning, "We met like rain-drops in the air.. .", AMsS, 2 p.
    [Includes attached magazine drawing.]
- Letters
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, England, to Mrs. Skinner, [1835]; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he is pleased and flattered that she will present him at Lady Arundel's hall; recalls meeting her and her celebrated friend [Jane] Porter, a writer.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, London, to Messrs. Harper, New York, [1836] Nov 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives the Harper Co. instructions for the republishing of Pencillings; says the volumes will be dedicated to John B. Van Schaick. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New York, to [Benjamin Franklin] Butler, Washington, 1838 Nov 2; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is writing a book on American scenery to be published in England; asks for his help in getting the duty reduced; makes an argument why the whole book should not be subject to duty.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Old Charlton, Kent, to Mary Russell Mitford, Reading, England, 1839 Aug 6; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he has dedicated "
    Tortesa the Usurer
    " to her without her permission; says that this play and "
    Bianca Visconti Or The Heart Overtasked
    " have been so successful in America that he could buy a beautiful farm on the Susquehanna; sends book by Miss Sedgwick; talks about a book on travel in the making; encourages her to give up all other writing in favor of play writing where she is so very successful; talks about a planned trip to the south of Europe; urges her to join him and his wife.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Dublin, Ireland, to James Henry Hackett, Dublin, [1840]; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says he has been to the theater in Dublin twice to see Hackett perform his Yankee characters; invites him to dine at the Rev. Dr. Wall's, where he will meet the Lord Mayor of Dublin and others.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New York, to Asa Hutchinson, New York, 1844 Aug 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Writes on behalf of a committee; mentions plans to give a free concert in New York in honor of General Morris who has done so much for the country; asks him to participate; includes signatures of Dr. Alban Goldsmith and George Endicott. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New York, to Abraham Hart, Carey & Hart, Philadelphia, 1846 Nov 19; ALS, 1 p.
    [Explains why certain poems of his do not lend themselves to drawings; says they express feelings and are not of a descriptive nature, but that others are suitable for Mr. Lentze's pencil; mentions a book review.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Glenmary, England, to Rev. John Gorham Palfrey, Boston, 1840 Jul 8; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses poetry that Willis promises to write for
    North American Review
    , sooner or later; mentions the high regard
    The North American Review
    enjoys in England. ]
  - N. Willis, Cambridge, to "My Dear Sir", 1849 May 14; ALS, 3 p.
    [Complains that his lectures and meetings at Cambridge take up all his time; mentions correspondent's work on a collection of Egyptian and Moorish plates belonging to Willis.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Highland Terrace, to Elizabeth Oakes Smith, 1852 Oct 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [States that the
    Home Journal
    is always at her service.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Benson John Lossing, [ New York], 1853 Sep 14; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses some of his verses and the imminent birth of a daughter or son.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to George Pope Morris, [ Philadelphia or New York], 1854 Mar; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his recovery from illness, the publication of a piece in Morris' periodical, and painter [Lawrence] who "makes everybody look as they will look in Heaven."]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Epes Sargent, [ Boston], 1854 Nov 26; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses "
    Lysteria
    , " a dramatic poem; asks him who the author is; finds fault with an engraving of himself; wants Mr. Smith, the engraver, to change the eye area, the under lip, thicken the hair, etc.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to [Catherine Ann Ware] Warfield, [ Natchez], 1854 Dec 3; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses a book she wants to sell to publisher; says he is so disgusted with negotiating bargains with publishers that he has somebody else do it for him; sympathizes with her; says that
    The Home Journal
    will do its best to ensure the book's success once it is published.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to James T. Fields, 1855 Jun 22; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for a chronicle of his visit, which was glowingly written about by Mrs. Harry Otis; talks about his Dedication Hymn and a letter from Dr. [Beattie], London, regarding it; hopes that Fields will "insert" it somewhere; describes a June morning.] (tipped in book,
    The Bryant Festival at the Century
    )
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to the Rev. E. Peabody, 1856 Jan 23; ALS, 4 p.
    [Praises [Ephraim?] Peabody's wonderful writing, which is worth collecting; talks about his "brain-troubles"; says he has been advised by his physician to stop writing for several years or risk sudden death; chooses to take the risk rather than endure intellectual idleness; speaks about
    says that all entries do not meet his high standards; invites the Peabody family to visit his house.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild>, to George Pope Morris, [ New York], 1856 Mar 23; ALS, 1 p.
    [Thanks him for gossiping letter and asks for more of the same; reports on a novel in progress; mentions the frozen Susquehanna river. ] (A portion of the letter has been cut out because it obtained an obscene sentence.)
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to James T. Fields, New York or Boston, 1857 Aug 4; ALS, 1 p.
    [Pleads with him to "give the world your likeness," namely, allow bearer of letter, [Mathew] Brady, to take his picture.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild>, to Nathaniel Ingersoll Bowditch, 1857 Aug 6; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is pleased to have received Bowditch's book
    Suffolk Surnames
    states that excerpts from it have already appeared in
    , but he will speak of it again.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Thomas Raynesford Lounsbury, [ Yale University], 1858 Mar 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he cannot help him with inquiries; offers "boyish" compositions he wrote in 1825, his Sophmore year; hopes they might be of help.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to [Theodore Sedgwick] Fay, [ New York], 1858 May 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says that letter will be presented to Fay by New York lawyer James [B.] Thayer, who is to sail to Europe; states that Thayer would like to introduce George Green to Fay.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New Bedford, to H. Prescott, Boston, 1859 Jan 27; ALS, 2 p.
    [Regrets not to have met Prescott, a person of "sovereign genius," during his stay in Boston. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to [John Williamson] Palmer, Baltimore, 1859 Feb 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses piece by Mrs. Palmer on Shakespeare; regrets not being able to use it in
    . ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Almont Barnes, Carthage, New York, 1859 Mar 11; ALS, 2 p. w/env
    [Discusses Barnes' poem ["
    The Eagle's Feather
    "] which Willis will probably publish.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to [John Williamson] Palmer, [ Baltimore], 1859 Apr 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Requests autograph; sends one of the stanzas Palmer speaks of.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to [John Williamson] Palmer, [ Baltimore], 1859 Jun 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends autograph of poem "
    Saturday afternoon
    "; acknowledges receipt of two books.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Osmond Tiffany, [ Baltimore], 1859 Jun 11; ALS, 1 p.
    [Acknowledges the receipt of a [book]; says he will look for Tiffany's name in review articles.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, [ Washington], to James T. Fields, Paris, France, 1859 Sep 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he would like Fields to go to the English Embassy and ask for the address of Lady Jenkins, one of the world's most charming women, widow of Sir Richard Jenkins, formerly president of the East India Company. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Anne Lynch Botta, 1860 Apr 21; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says that his household has been overwhelmed with company, "all up-hillers," and his wife is now sick in bed; says he cannot comply with Botta's request to write his own obituary; sends her some scraps which he has gathered over the years, which seem to him discriminating or noteworthy; speaks of his wife's great affection for Botta.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to John Williamson Palmer, [ Baltimore], 1860 Jul 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is not able to help him with his inquiry; suggests approaching Henry Tuckerman with the matter.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Miss Faulkner, 1860 Sep 12; LS, 1 p.
    [Printed form-letter; tells her in a very polite way that he does not feel like writing her a personal letter.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Frank W. Ballard, 1860 Oct 5; ALS, 2 p.
    [Thanks him for a flattering letter.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to George Pope Morris, [ New York], 1860 Dec 18; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends him what he believes is his best "Scripture Poem" ever; asks him to take it to Bonner.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, [ Washington], to Mrs. Charles Eames, [ Washington], 1862 Jan 5; ALS, 1 p.
    [Responds to her claim that he lives in a halo and that she does not know what his face looks like anymore by sending his "likeness"; walks past her home 6 times a day on his way to and from Willard's for his meals; looks up to her window for a smile, in vain.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to one of his children, 1863 Oct 13; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is not feeling well and waits for "Mamma"; sends a letter from young Stace; signs letter, "your affectionate papa."]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to George Pope Morris, 1863 Oct 27; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses Morris' health, Willis' family matters,
    , increase in advertising; mentions Epes Sargent. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, [ New York], to Teresa Viele, [ New York], 1866 Feb 26; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says that an attack of vertigo kept him from writing her; sends early copies from [
    ]; encourages her to write more; mentions visitors to his home, including Mrs. Henry Hills, Mrs. Henry Grinnell, and Anne Lynch Botta. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Woolrich, England, to Sir Charles, [1836] Mar 22; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses difficulties with Captain Frederick Marryat and an avoided duel, the serious illness of his wife, and his tentative plans to return to America, depending on the recovery of his wife; mentions Jane Porter's presence and his indebtedness to Sir Charles.]
  - Cornelia Grinnell Willis, Idlewild, to Fitz-Green Halleck, May 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Writes for her husband who injured his hand in a fall; says they look forward to Halleck's visit to Idlewild. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Glenmary, to R. [Londen], Jun 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Expresses condolences after the death of Londen's wife; includes ALS, Londen to Willis, on verso, acknowledging condolence letter.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to "My dear Haight", Jul [3]; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses a misplaced letter, and how hard Willis is working; comments on mutual acquaintances.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New York, to Charles S. Ogden, Philadelphia, Jul 11; LS, w/ANS 1 p.
    [Says he is overburdened by work; decides to send him this preprinted letter; tells him in a autograph note that he does not have Poe's autograph.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Thomas Bailey Aldrich, Aug 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends requested letter having to do with publishing business.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Glenmary, to George Virtue, England, Nov 11; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends fifth portion of "
    Ireland
    "; says it should reach England by boat December 1; mentions [James] Grant. ]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to James Parton, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Declines invitation due to overload of work; compliments him on his last two papers which were "exemplary good."]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New York, to George Pope Morris, New York, Jul 31; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses
    copies for Madame Calderon de la Barca, wife of Spanish minister; says copies are to be sent to an address on Long Island; reports on his improving health.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Idlewild, to Samuel Bulkley Ruggles, n. d.; ALS, 4 p.
    [Urges him to send forgotten other half of a poem by [Regis De Trobriand]; says he would love to publish it; declines trip to Nantucket as he has too many houseguests at the moment; urges him to visit again in the fall, to join Mrs. Hills and Mrs. Otis and have a "time."]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, Home Journal, to Abraham Hart, Carey & Hart, Publishers, Philadelphia, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses business; asks them to date and sign an enclosed document.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, New York, to Abraham Hart, Carey & Hart, Philadelphia, n. d.; ALS, 3 p.
    [Discusses business, a new edition of his poems; agrees to their terms, which are the same ones they give Longfellow, but wants to revise and refine his poems before publication; asks for $300 advance; encloses drawing of one of his poems; says same young artist will do any number of such drawings, cheap.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to [ T. C. Hausard], n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Discusses printing of "
    " and "Bianca."]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to James T. Fields, Boston, n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Introduces Patterson, who will deliver the letter by hand, to Fields; says Patterson is the editor of the [Anglo-American] and "one of our choicest spirits, as well as best critics."]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to Ph. H. Brown, Esq., n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Responds to request for autograph.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to [ R. Gilmor], n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Promises to visit him to renew their acquaintance; remembers his kindness in former years.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to Anne Lynch Botta, [ New York], n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends check for 3 tickets she sent him; compliments her on last night's dancing.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to [Mrs. Butler], n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends her promised verses, possibly AMs poem beginning, "My Mother! in thy prayer tonight.. ."; says he will send lines on the President's grandchild at a better moment.]
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis to "Dear Sir", n. d.; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs him that he is ready to receive him tonight between seven and eight.]
- Photographs and prints
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, standing, with hat and cane, [1863]; Photo
    [Include AN on verso, Willis to one of his sons.]
  - Magazine photo, Nathaniel Parker Willis, head and shoulders, Drawing
    [Includes attached AMsS poem beginning, "We met like rain-drops.. ."]
  - Ashland [a house] tipped to sheet with AMsS poem, " Impromptu ", Engraving
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, standing, with hat and cane, Engraving
  - Nathaniel Parker Willis, head and shoulders, Engraving